In this video, we will be talking about
circuits
and Ohm's law. If you have taken science
in
grade 9, this might be review for you, but
this
will be further applied to high school
physics,
especially in AP and IB.
So, first of all, what is Ohm's law?
Ohm's law states that the total voltage is
equal
to I times R, where I is the current and R
is
the resistance. Resistance.
Resistance is measured in ohms, current is
measured
in amperes or amps, and voltage is
in volts. And
this formula can be applied to solving
values
we need in a circuit. Now, there are two
different
types of circuits, and they can be
combined
to make one big circuit, like in this
case.
These are series circuits and parallel
circuits.
Series circuits are circuits that are in a
series.
The voltage goes around, around the
circuit,
whereas a parallel circuit, the voltage is
going
parallel to each other that way.
So, there are rules that we have to do to
follow
for a series circuit and a parallel
circuit.
First of all, the current in a series
circuit
is the same everywhere. I1 equals I2
equals
I3, and so on.
Wherever you are in the series circuit,
the
current is the same. However, in a
parallel
circuit, the total current is equal to the
sum
of all the currents in each branch.
So, I total equals I1 plus I2 plus dot dot
dot, and if this was a parallel, this
would
be I1 and this would be I2.
Voltage, however, is quite the opposite.
The voltage in a series circuit is the sum
of
all the total voltages, V1 plus V2 plus
V3.
However, in a parallel circuit, the
voltage
is the same for everywhere. In each
branch,
there is the same voltage.
Now, resistance. In a series circuit, the
resistance
is a cumulative sum, same thing as the
voltage.
So, R total equals R1 plus R2 plus
R3 plus so on.
So, if let's say we had multiple
resistors,
the total resistance of this circuit would
be
the sum of all of these. However, in a
parallel
circuit, the total resistance is the
reciprocal.
The reciprocal of the total resistance is
the
sum of all the reciprocals of the
resistance.
This means that 1 over R total equals 1
over
R1 plus 1 over R2 plus 1 over R3 and so
on.
So, if we want to derive this formula
further,
we can do it.
And isolating for R total, we get 1, 1,
sorry, we flip it, so it's R total equals
over 1 over R1 plus 1 over R2 plus 1
over R3 plus dot dot dot.
And if we further want to simplify it, we
can,
but I'll just leave it here because there
is
no use for the simplifying by getting a
common
denominator, flipping it. So, now that we
know
a brief estimate of how to calculate each
of
these values in a circuit and Ohm's Law,
we
can have, let's look at this example
question
over here. So, over here we have a
circuit.
The first thing I notice is that there is
a
parallel circuit here and everything else
is
in series. This is in series.
So, what we first want to do is calculate
the
current that flows through R1. So, we want
A.
Well, we know the resistance and we know V
equals
IR. I'll use green for this.
V equals IR, so I equals V over R.
We know R because at R1, R is just 24.
However, we need the voltage.
Well, in a parallel circuit, the voltage
is
the same for both branches. So, basically
what
that means is that the voltage here would
be
equal to the voltage here or the voltage
here
because, sorry, not the voltage there,
would
be the voltage here, the voltage right
before
it goes into the parallel circuit. So,
basically
we need to calculate the voltage of our
series
circuit. Now, we know that the voltage in
a
series circuit is the sum of all the
voltages
and we only have one voltage because we
only
have one battery, which is here.
So, and that's 48 ohms.
So, if this is 48 ohms, oops, sorry, this
should
be in volts. So, if this is 48 volts, then
according to our rule over here, this
would
also be 48 volts. And now we can just plug
it
in, 48 over 24, and that would give us 2
amps, and that would be our answer for
that
question. Now, the next part wants us to
calculate
the total current in the circuit. Well,
the
total current in the circuit, we first
need
to find the total voltage in the circuit
and
then the total resistance. Let's first
derive
a formula for the total current. I total
equals
V total over R total.
Now, let's first get V total.
Like I said before, the total current in
this
circuit is just 48 volts because there are
no
other batteries. So, V total is 48 volts.
Now, the total resistance, let's see, we
first
need to find the total resistance of this
parallel
circuit. And that basically, we can
imagine
it as whatever we get as the total
resistance
in the parallel circuit is just one big
resistor
that kind of goes like this.
And then after that, using this law, we
can
add that total resistance with R3.
So, basically, R total is equal to, well,
in
the parallel circuit first, it is equal to
over R1 plus 1 over R2.
And that would be the total resistance of
this
parallel circuit. Now, let's treat that as
one
resistance. So, we have another resistor
over
here, which is R3.
So, the total resistance in the whole
circuit
would be this plus R3.
And when we calculate it, it's 1 over 24
and
12. So, 1 over 1 over 24 plus 1 over 12
plus
R3 would be 12. And when you calculate
this,
you would get the total resistance of the
thing,
which is 20 ohms.
So, now we have the total resistance and
the
total voltage, so we can actually
calculate
the total current. I total equals 48 volts
over 20 ohms.
So, that would give us 2.4 amps.
That would be your final answer. So,
usually
in a lot of series problems, as you may
have
seen in grade 9, you would have to combine
the
parallel circuits into one big piece, and
then
you would continue to do whatever you're
doing,
for example, going on to a series circuit.
That's all for today's video.
I hope you learned something or reviewed,
and
we'll see you next time talking about
Kirchhoff's
Law.